I wish to remind you that next week,
we're going to take all the chips and
the logic gates we've built in
previous weeks of this course,
and we're going to assemble
them together into a unified
hardware platform which we call the,
the Hack computer.
Now, in order to set up to this
very engaging and interesting
construction work, we decided that
this week we have to give you
a good overview of what is it
exactly that you're going to build.
And that's one reason why we decided
to explore all these notions of
low-level programming the Hack assembly
language, and the Hack hardware,
because at this very low-level of
operation, everything is tightly coupled.
When you build the computer,
you have think about its instruction set.
When you design the machine language or
the instruction set,
you have to think about the computer.
There's no way to avoid it.
So once again,
the purpose of of this week was,
first of all,
to expose you to low-level programming but
we also wanted to give you a feeling of a,
of the harder platform that
you're actually going to
implement in the next week.
And this is also the purpose
of of Project 4.
In Project 4 you will write two programs
that will let you put your hands on,
on the hardware and, and
program it in a, in a very low-level,
i, in a level which is almost
connected to the machine.
So we'll do this by writing two
relatively simple pro, programs.
The first program will affect
some algebraic manipulation, and
the second program will
interact with the user
operating on both the screen and
the keyboard.
All right, so without further ado here is
the first program which is called Mult.
And the purpose of this program
is to compute the product,
or the multiplication, of R0 and R1.
So here's a screenshot of this
program executing in the CPU Emulator.
In fact, it's a screenshot of
the end of this program's execution.
If you look carefully
at the top of the RAM,
you will see that RAM 0 is 6,
RAM 1 is 7, and RAM 2 is 42.
And that's exactly what this
program is supposed to do,
to multiply the first two registers
in the memory and compute the,
and, and, and place the product
of these two numbers in RAM 2.
So the assumption is that once the user
has loaded this program into the data
memory into the instruction memory,
the user also places two numbers
in RAM 0 and RAM, RAM 1.
Clicks the Go button or
the Play button starts playing and if
everything works nicely the program will
compute the product of these two numbers.
On the right-hand side,
in the screen area we see a script
that we supply together with this project.
And the script is designed to to test
the program using some pairs of numbers
that that we made up.
And obviously you can explore the script
as well in order to see what kind of tests
we are going to subject
your programmer to.
And you know, this is maybe also the place
to point out that in the simulator,
in, in the CPU Emulator, we use the screen
as sort of a multi-purpose device.
Sometimes it works as
a real physical screen.
Sometimes, we use it as a window
to display our test scripts,
test scripts and, and so on.
All right, so once again, in this area
you see the input the two inputs and
the, the output of the program.
And I guess the question that burns right
now is how do we write such a program?
Well recall, that the, the Hack machine
language doesn't have
a multiplication operation.
All we have is addition and subtraction.
So we're faced with a challenge of
expressing a multiplication operation
using addition and subtraction.
I don't think that I have
to say much more than this,
I can give you perhaps only one more hint.
You will have to use a loop.
And using this loop,
you will somehow compute the the result.
By the way those of you who will choose to
take part two of this course, I meant to
that as part two, will also go through the
process of developing an operating system.
And one thing that our operating system
is going to deliver, to deliver is a,
is a math library that features all
sorts of mathematical operations,
and one of these mathematical
operations is going to be multiply.
And the multiplication algorithm that
you will use in the operating system is,
extremely efficient and something that we
don't expect you to do in this exercise.
In this exercise we simply expect you to
somehow multiply the two numbers and,
you know, maybe you can try to do it as,
as efficiently as you can.
But we don't expect you to
get out of your way and
come up with some very fancy algorithms
to, to carry out multiplication.
All right, so this the first assignment.
And the second assignment is to
write a simple interactive program
that performs the following operation.
This program listens to the keyboard, and
as long as the user does nothing
with the keyboard, nothing happens.
But once the user touches a key on
the keyboard, any key, you know,
once you touch a key look what happens.
The program blackens
the screen completely.
And once you lift your finger from the
keyboard, the screen becomes again clear.
You put your finger again
on any key on the keyboard,
the key the screen becomes black.
You take your you take your finger away,
the screen becomes clear.
That's what this program is doing.
It is going through some,
some sort of infinite loop that
listens to the keyboard all the time and
acts accordingly.
So actually we have here
two separate challenges.
One of them is to probe the keyboard and,
and understand what the, you know,
whether or not any key is pressed.
And the other challenge is to be able to
blacken the screen or whiten the screen,
which is essentially the same
operation in one we write a certain
value to the memory map and in the other
operation we, we write some other value.
What makes this exercise somewhat easy
is the fact that we operate
on the entire memory map.
So we don't have to be picky and
select certain pixels to turn on and
off, we simply sort of a shotgun approach,
we either turn on all the pixels or
turn off all the pixels.
In that respect the program is
is not terribly complicated and
in general it's not, it's not really
a terribly complicated program.
But it's kind of fun.
You know, it allows you to see how you,
you can control peripheral
devices using a,
a standard Hack machine language called.
All right, so here is the general
implementation strategy.
Listen to the keyboard.
To blacken or create a screen,
we write code that fills the entire screen
memory map with white or black pixels.
And in order to do this,
we have to address every register
in the memory map, and
we do it using some sort of a loop.
That works with pointers in a very
similar way to what we did in
in the previous unit when we
discussed pointers manipulation.
So you really have all the firepower
that you need in order to,
to implement this particular program.
In order to test this program on
the CPU Emulator, make sure that
the no animation selection is is selected,
and
also, we cannot provide a test
script that tests this program,
or, or we can, but we,
we thought that it would be too com,
too complicated, so
you simply have to test it.
As I di, demonstrated, you know, put
your finger down, put your finger up and
hope that the screen will be blackened or
whitened and so on.
You can also think, if you want,
you can think about some fancy ways
to blacken or whiten the screen.
You know,
instead of going line-by-line, you wa,
you may want to go column-by-column.
You wa, you may want to create some this,
this will be quite challenging to
create some drawing you know swirls.
I don't know.
You can, you use your imagination.
Do whatever you want in order
to blacken or whiten the screen.
And and that's actually what is expected
from you in in this particular program.
All right I want to describe some general
things about the overall
program development process or
cycle when you want to write programs
in the Hack machine language.
First of all,
your programs are going to reside
within regular text files that you
can write with any text editor.
So, you invoke your favorite text editor.
You write the program.
You save it using the extension asm.
And by convention we give our programs
names that begin with capital letters so
we give it a name, .asm.
And then you load this program
as is into the CPU Emulator.
As I explained before, the CPU Emulator
has this very nice service.
That when you load the program it
automatically translates the program into
binary code.
So you can next run the program
on the CPU Emulator and
ask yourself if you're
satisfied with the results.
If so, you are done.
You can submit the program to us and
if you are unsatisfied with the program
which will be a probably the case in
the first few iterations of the debugging,
then you will, you fix the program.
You look for errors and you fix
the errors and you fix them by going back
into the text editor, you know, working
in the editor, saving the program again.
Reloading it into the CPU Emulator,
and so on.
So it's quite convenient to
have two windows open on the,
on your screen at the same time, the text
editor here, CPU Emulator there, and
you can easily, you know,
move between the two but
don't forget to load your updated
program after you you fix it.
The error diagnostics of
the CPU Emulator is quite primitive.
So when you load the program into
the CPU Emulator, if there's a syntax
error in this program, the CPU Emulator
will simply refuse to load it.
It will issue some cryptic error
message something like oh,
it will give you some very important
information and to give you the line
number with error occurred and
the first error that was found.
And then you can go into this line
number and and fix the problem.
And once you, you are done with the,
with the syntax e, errors,
well, then the real problems begin,
you know?
These are the run-time errors,
which are much harder to detect.
And you typically detect them by
watching the execution of your program,
seeing that something
does not work properly.
And then once again you have
to go through the same cycle.
And fix your program until it
works to your satisfaction.
So this is the general mechanics
of developing a program
using a CPU Emulator and a text editor.
And as you see it, it's quite,
it's quite simple and friendly.
All right finally I want to say
a few words about best practice and
advice on do's and do, and don'ts.
There's no reason really
to think about a machine
language programs as some sort of a,
a strange animal.
It's yet another example of a,
a programming art effect.
And all the principles that
applied to writing programs
in a high-level language
also apply at the low level.
We expect your programs to be short,
or not unnecessarily long.
They should be short, they should be
efficient, they should be elegant, and
they should be self-describing.
So we expect you to document the programs,
but do it by using some judgment.
You know, don't over-document the program.
The best, I think thing to do is
simply to look at our examples and
to follow something similar,
so, you know, typically
we use some high-level
operation to describe you know?
We start a comment, we write something
like, here we're going to say,
if i is greater than n, goto,
and then, we write the 6 or
7 instructions in machine code that
actually implement this this semantics.
Now here's some very important technical
tips that will make your life easier.
First of all, you must use
symbolic variables and labels.
You know, otherwise your
programs will be helplessly and
hopelessly complex, and and cryptic.
So, if you want to go to somewhere
in your program, use a label.
If you want to store something
repetitively, make up a variable name.
So, when you're done writing the program,
you know, look at it,
and make sure that you don't see any
actual educes there, you have to make
sure that everything is symbolic, you
know, this is one very important ritual,
of well-written machine language,
language programs.
When you invent your variables and
your labels, as usual in programming,
use sensible names.
You know, don't make cryptic names like
gu5 3 percent or something like this.
Use instead something like loop end,
stop, positive, negative.
You know, depending on what
is it that you want to do,
try to use sensible label names and,
likewise, variable names.
You know, use nice names, like i,
end, some, count, and, and so on.
Now, when you declare or, or
when you use these variable names,
use lower-case for variables and
upper-case for labels.
If you go back to our program examples,
you will see that all the labels,
you know typically words like END and
STOP were uppercase, and
all the variables i, n, x,
y and so on were lower case.
If you follow this convention, which
is not required by the way, you know,
it's, it's not something that they,
that the assembler cares about.
But if you use this convention you
will have a very easy time for
yourself to distinguish
between variables and labels.
So when you see an @ command when
an A command, when you see something about
@sum, if the sum is lower-case,
you know it's a variable.
If it's uppercase, you know that we
mean to go to a label called SUM.
And finally, use indentation.
Once again, follow the examples
that we gave in the previous units,
and make sure that your programs
are good-looking and easy to read.
And it's always recommend, recommended,
to start with pseudo code.
Writing machine level code
is always challenging.
And your life will be much
easier if you first, you know,
make up the program or
write the program using some,
some sort of a high-level language
that you can make up for yourself.
Or once again, follow our examples.
Once the program works
nicely in pseudo code, and
this something that you have to, to check
on, on a piece of paper, you can then
translate it into machine language and
continue the debugging process.
All right where do you
find everything you need?
Well as usual,
you go to the NAND to Tetris website.
You look at Project 4.
All the files that you need for
this exercise are described in for
this project.
I'm sorry,
are described in in this webpage, and
there's no need to download anything,
because if you downloaded the software
suite at the beginning of the course,
you now have on your personal computer,
you have a directory called project/04.
And this directory already
contains all the files that
you have to use and and
manipulate in in Project 4.
So this has been
the the unit in which we we
hopefully give you some tips on how to how
to write the, the programs in Project 4.
And we now go on to
the last unit in this week
in which we reflect on what we
did during the entire week.